<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record label="Virginia 1808 House of Delegates, Amelia County" type="General" iteration="First Ballot" date="1808" election_id="va.houseofdelegates.amelia.1808" handle="10427/33049" xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="House of Delegates" office_id="ON063" scope="State">
		<role title="Delegate" scope="County">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="Thomas Perkinson" name_id="PT0086" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="1"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="Bathurst Randolph" name_id="RB0066" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="2"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="James Robertson" name_id="RJ0627" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="3"/>
				<candidate name="James P. Cocke" name_id="CJ1080" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="4"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2011-09-16">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="186" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="163" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="3" vote_total="158" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="4" vote_total="128" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.08626" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.08627" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.08628" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">The Enquirer (Richmond, VA) and The Virginia Argus (Richmond, VA) list 189 votes for Thomas Perkinson and 166 votes for Bathurst Randolph.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">Thomas Perkinson and Bathurst Randolph were initially elected.  James Robertson contested the election of Bathurst Randolph and was successful.  James Robertson duly elected, as resolved by the committee on Privileges and Elections as reported in The Enquirer (Richmond, VA), December 13, 1808.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Extracts From the Journal of the House of Delegates. Tuesday, Dec. 6...A petition was presented and read from James Robertson, of the county of Amelia, compaining of the undue election and return of Bathurst Randolph, one of the delegates returned to serve in this present General Assembly from said county...Referred to the committee of Privileges and Elections...Wednesday, Dec. 7...Mr. Wooding from the committee of Privileges and Elections made the following report:  The Committee of Privileges and Elections have according to order had under their consideration the petition of James Robertson, jun. complaining of the undue election of Bathurst Randolph, returned to serve as a delegate for the county of Amelia, to them referred, agreed upon a report and come to the following resolutions thereupon:  It appears to your committee, that at the election held for the county of Amelia, in April last, there were four polls kept, two of which gave B. Randolph a majority of eight votes, one a majority of five, and one a majority of four; and that the petitioner James Robertson, jun. admitted the polls giving to B. Randolph the majority of eight votes to be correctly kept.  It appears also to your dommittee, from the depositions of George Baldwin, commissioner for the county of Amelia, and John T. Leigh, deputy sheriff for said county, that there are twenty-three voters, viz: - Zachariah Hendrick...William Waters, whose names are not upon the land book, and who voted for Bathurst Randolph.  It appears also to your committee, from the admission or Bathurst Randolph, that the votes of James Lockett...Zachariah Hendrick, are illegal votes.  Resolved, as the opinion of this committee, that the votes of Zachariah Hendrick...Zachariah Butler, ought to be expunged from the poll of Bathurst Randolph, because they are illegal votes.  The poll of B. Randolph stood thus: 166 at the close of the election, deduct illegal votes 28, good votes 138.  The poll of James Robertson stood thus: 158 at the close of the election deduct nothing -- good votes 158.  Resolved, therefore, as the opinion of this committee, That the poll ought to stand thus: For Bathurst Randolph 138 - James Robertson, jr. 158.  By which, it appears, that Jas. Robertson, jr. had a majority of legal votes, independent of the admission on the part of Bathurst Randolph, and that he was duly elected to represent the county of Amelia, in this present General Assembly.  Resolved, also, as the opinion of this committee, That the peition of James Robertson, jr. complaining of the undue election of Bathurst Randolph, returned to serve as a Delegate from the county of Amelia for this present General Assembly, is reasonable.  The said resolutions being severally read a second time, were agreed to by the House.  The Enquirer (Richmond, VA).  December 13, 1808.</note>			
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Virginia" geog_id="vas">
				<sub_unit type="County" name="Amelia" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="186" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="163" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="3" vote="158" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="4" vote="128" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.08626" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.08627" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.08628" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role></office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.08626">Amelia County Poll Book.  Library of Virginia, Richmond.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.08628">The Enquirer (Richmond, VA).  May 3, 1808.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.08627">The Virginia Argus (Richmond, VA).  May 3, 1808.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Enquirer (Richmond, VA).  December 13, 1808.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Leonard, Cynthia Miller, ed.  The General Assembly of Virginia, July 30, 1619 - January 11, 1978: A Bicentennial Register of Members.  Richmond: Virginia State Library, 1978.</reference>
</election_record>
