<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" label="Massachusetts 1802 U.S. House of Representatives, Suffolk District" type="General" iteration="First Ballot" date="1802-11" election_id="ma.uscongress.suffolk.1802" handle="10427/27804" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="U.S. House of Representatives" office_id="ON125" scope="Federal">
		<role title="U.S. Congressman" scope="District">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="William Eustis" name_id="EW0031" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="1"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="John Quincy Adams" name_id="AJ0043" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="2"/>
				<candidate name="Joseph Heard" name_id="HJ0413" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="3"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2014-09-04">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="1898" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="1839" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="3" vote_total="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00262" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Yesterday the inhabitants of this State assembled in their respective towns to elect their Representatives in Congress. In Suffolk District, composed of the towns of Boston, Hingham, Hull, Chelsea, Malden, Medford, and Charlestown, the Hon. J.Q. ADAMS was the Federal Republican Candidate;--and the Hon. WM. EUSTIS, the Democratic Candidate. ... COMMUNICATION. Yesterday the election for a Representative in Congress took place in this district.--It was a rainy uncomfortable day; and the consequence probably will be, the loss of Mr. ADAMS' election. The votes were as follows--for Mr. ADAMS 1496, for Mr. EUSTIS 1430. Last April the federal ticket for Governor and Senators had 2372, the democratic 1498. From a comparison of their numbers, we see a degree of negligence among the Federalists inexcusable and alarming. Was it blind confidence of success that framed excuses for staying at home, or was it the weather? In either case, let those qualified voters, whose names remain unchecked for such reasons, answer it to themselves and to their country. The time will most assuredly come, if they are thus heedless of their own true interests, when staying at home will not secure them from the wasteful, plundering hand of Democracy."  New-England Palladium (Boston, MA).  November 2, 1802.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"CONGRESSIONAL ELECTION. Suffolk.--Hon. WILLIAM EUSTIS, (Republican) is chosen by a majority of 59 votes ... Among the arts of the able editor of the Centinel, we have been amused to notice his manner of stating the majority of votes by which the Republican candidates are chosen. Doctor EUSTIS had 1899, Mr. ADAMS 1840. There was not a single scattering vote. The Centinel says 'Doctor EUSTIS is chosen by a Majority of 29 votes.' This is done by adding the whole number together and taking more than half, as necessary to a choice. Would it not be quite as fair to deduct 1840 from 1889, and give the balance as the Majority. By this mode of calculation, Doctor EUSTIS is chosen by a Majority of 59 votes."  The National Aegis (Worcester, MA).  November 10, 1802.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Republicanism Triumphant. We are happy to have the pleasure this day of announcing to our readers the complete triumph of Repubicanism at the Head-quarters of Good principles--And we congratulate you on the agreeable Intelligence, which whispers peace, and reconciliation in your ears--Instead of opposition and discord. thus you see, merit, must eventually have its reward.--And your exertions, Republicans, have been crowned with honor, and success in the re-election of the unimpeachable DR. WILLIAM EUSTIS to represent you in Congress. All we have to regret in the business, is, that the weather was so unfavorable as to deter many of our (now infirm) HEROES of SEVENTY FIVE in this town, from the satisfaction of giving in their votes for the Man, whose whole life has been devoted to the cause of humanity and his country ... MASSACHUSETTS CONGRESSIONAL ELECTION. Effects of Republican energy, over Anti-Republican tendency ... At the election two years since, Mr. Quincey, the Federal candidate, had 175 votes more than Dr. Eustis--And notwithstanding the monstrous exertions of the Federalists, in their papers for four weeks past, and the whole weight of Bank, and Mercantile influence on their side, in distributing votes on the ground of election--Notwithstanding the weight of character and name of their only candidate that could be opposed to Dr. Eustis--Notwithstanding the Federalists in the General Court, who made the districting bill, shifted the Republican ground, and took up a federal position--Notwithstanding the politeness of Judge Sedgwick, Thatcher, and the Hon. Timothy Bigelow Esq. who paraded Faneuil Hall, during the voting, and notwithstanding the Giant of the Law came up the back stairs with his vote, the federal votes have decreased 109--this is full proof that reason is fast overpowering delusion, and light and truth will finally prevail. ... The re-election of Doct. EUSTIS, as member of Congress for Suffolk District, is perhaps the most important triumph of republicanism that has taken place in New-England, since the adoption of the federal government. Federalism (as it is falsly called) has been attacked in its strong holds, and been defeated. No character, we presume to say, of the federal party, could have been brought forward with better prospects of success than John Quincey Adams, the son of the late President of the United States. We doubt very much, whether even the father himself, would have been more successful had he been the Doctor's opponent; for the friends of the one are unquestionably the friends of the other. The 'knowing' Major asserted, a short time previous to the election, 'that even to doubt for a moment the success of Mr. Adams, would be worse than treason.' Can it be possible major, that the 'Washington and Adams ticket,' has not prevailed in the highly federal district of Suffolk? Yes it is possible! and thank heaven, the citizens of the United States in general, have their eyes fixed on measures; more than on MEN, however great and conspicuous their characters may have been."  Republican Gazetteer (Boston, MA).  November 3, 1802.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"We have copied the following articles from the NATIONAL AEGIS, (a paper printed at Worcester, Mass.) of the 3rd instant. They will be highly pleasing to every friend of our present administration, ... Dr. Eustis, the republican candidate in Suffolk county, is unquestionably chosen."  The Republican, and Petersburg Advertiser (Petersburg, VA)</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"If Dr. EUSTIS'S abilities in politics are questioned by any class of citizens, they cannot be doubted in his other profession; as he has twice, successively, cured the people of the Quincy!"  Columbian Minerva (Dedham, MA).  November 16, 1802.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"'Dr. William Eustis ... [is] chosen Representative to the next Congress from Massachusetts, in opposition to John Quincy Adams ... In the town of Boston, Mr. Adams had 1496 votes, and Mr. Eustis 1430. It is stated that there were at least 700 federalists in the town of Boston who did not attend the meeting, partly owing to the tempestuous weather, and partly to a confidence that their votes were unnecessary.' [Con. Gaz.] 700 Federalists!--This account originated in Boston, by our Federal Editors. See! it looses nothing by flying to the New-London Federalist, Mr. Green. And by the time it reaches the Editors of the N.Y. Evening Post, it is probable it will be, 'A trick of the infamous Republicans!'"  Columbian Minerva (Dedham, MA).  November 30, 1802.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Massachusetts" geog_id="null">
				<sub_unit type="District" name="Suffolk" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="1898" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="1839" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="3" vote="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<sub_unit type="County" name="Middlesex" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" vote="352" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" vote="249" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="3" vote="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<sub_unit type="Town" name="Charlestown" geog_id="null">
							<result candidate_ref="1" vote="244" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<result candidate_ref="2" vote="133" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<result candidate_ref="3" vote="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00262" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						</sub_unit>
						<sub_unit type="Town" name="Malden" geog_id="null">
							<result candidate_ref="1" vote="90" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<result candidate_ref="2" vote="21" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00262" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						</sub_unit>
						<sub_unit type="Town" name="Medford" geog_id="null">
							<result candidate_ref="1" vote="18" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<result candidate_ref="2" vote="95" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00262" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						</sub_unit>
					</sub_unit>
					<sub_unit type="County" name="Suffolk" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" vote="1546" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" vote="1590" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00262" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<sub_unit type="Town" name="Boston" geog_id="null">
							<result candidate_ref="1" vote="1430" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<result candidate_ref="2" vote="1496" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00262" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						</sub_unit>
						<sub_unit type="Town" name="Chelsea" geog_id="null">
							<result candidate_ref="1" vote="21" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<result candidate_ref="2" vote="15" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00262" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						</sub_unit>
						<sub_unit type="Town" name="Hingham" geog_id="null">
							<result candidate_ref="1" vote="83" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<result candidate_ref="2" vote="79" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00262" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						</sub_unit>
						<sub_unit type="Town" name="Hull" geog_id="null">
							<result candidate_ref="1" vote="12" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
							<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00262" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						</sub_unit>
					</sub_unit>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00262">Original Election Returns.  Massachusetts State Archives, Boston.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Columbian Minerva (Dedham, MA).  November 2, 1802.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">New-England Palladium (Boston, MA).  November 2, 1802.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Columbian Centinel. Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  November 3, 1802.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The National Aegis (Worcester, MA).  November 3, 1802.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Republican Gazetteer (Boston, MA).  November 3, 1802.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Columbian Minerva (Dedham, MA).  November 9, 1802.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The National Aegis (Worcester, MA).  November 10, 1802.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Columbian Minerva (Dedham, MA).  November 16, 1802.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Republican, and Petersburg Advertiser (Petersburg, VA).  November 16, 1802.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Columbian Minerva (Dedham, MA).  November 30, 1802.</reference>
</election_record>
