<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record label="Virginia 1811 U.S. House of Representatives, District 1" type="General" iteration="First Ballot" date="1811" election_id="va.uscongress.1.1811" handle="10427/33375" xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="U.S. House of Representatives" office_id="ON125" scope="Federal">
		<role title="U.S. Congressman" scope="District">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="William MacKinley" name_id="MW0394" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="1"/>
				<candidate name="Thomas Wilson" name_id="WT0140" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="2"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2011-11-03">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00620" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24354" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24359" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24363" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24365" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24368" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24375" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24378" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24380" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24386" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24387" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24389" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24394" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24396" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Thomas Wilson, Esq. the federal candidate for Congress in the district of Harrison, etc. (formerly represented by John G. Jackson, Esq.) is elected by a majority of 375 over his opponent William M'Kinley, Esq."  Norfolk Gazette and Publick Ledger (Norfolk, VA).  May 24, 1811.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"In Ohio District, the two counties of Ohio and Monogalia, gave...in 1811 Mr. Jackson...487, and the federal candidate 445."  Norfolk Gazette and Publick Ledger (Norfolk, VA).  April 28, 1813.  NOTE: The vote figures used in this quote are correct, but the candidates name is in error. Mr. Jackson was elected and served from March 4, 1803, to September 28, 1810 when he resigned.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Thomas Wilson, Esq. the Federal Republican Candidate for Congress is the district of Harrison, etc. (formerly represented by John G. Jackson, Esq.) is elected by a majority of 375 over his opponent William M'Kinley, Esq. a democrat."  Poulson's American Daily Advertiser (Philadelphia, PA).  May 27, 1811.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Thomas Wilson, a federalist, is elected member of Congress in the district lately represented by John G. Jackson, by a majority of 380 over Mr. McKinley his opponent."  The Virginia Argus (Richmond, VA).  May 27, 1811.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Mr. Wilson is listed as the successful candidate - the die however, is not positively cast in his favor.  By the last returns, he had a majority of more than 300; and there were but two counties, to wit Randolph and Brooke, to be heard from. - So, that in spite of the information of two intelligent papers, one of them too on the spot, we are afraid that Mr. McKinley is ousted."  The Enquirer (Richmond, VA).  May 10, 1811.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Federalism rising in Virginia ~ A gentleman from Virginia states that Mr. Wilson, the federal candidate, is elected to Congress, from J. G. Jackson's district, in opposition to Mr. M'Kinley, the present democratic representative."  New-York Herald (New York, NY).  May 1, 1811.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"We are informed by a correspondent that the election for a member of congress, in the six western counties of Virginia, lately represented by John G. Jackson, esq. has terminated in favor of Thomas Wilson, esq. the federal candidate. ~  The official returns from the five counties give Mr. Wilson a majority of 453 over Mr. M'Kinley, the democratic candidate.  M'Kinley will have a majority of from 50 to 100 votes, which will leave Mr. Wilson a net majority of at least 350 votes."  The Supporter (Chillocothe), May 4, 1811; and New-York Herald (New York, NY), May 18, 1811.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Thomas Wilson Esq. of Morgantown, a Federalist, is elected to congress for the district formerly represented by John G. Jackson Esquire."  Fayette and Greene Spectator (Uniontown, PA).  May 16, 1811.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Clarksburg, April 19th. 1811.  My Dear Sir. Your favor of the 12th. reached me on the 16th.  The Preceding day was that of our Election, on which the District turned and I am sorry to say the Federal Candidate obtained a majority of 102 votes - he is elected.  Mr. McKinley never was here before and his coming ruined our hopes, as his manners and [etc.] are unpopular, and here the People vote for men more than principles.  On the morning of the election I was taken up for the Assembly and voted in, which I truly regret as my old friend Prunty was dropped [John Prunty a member of the Virginia state ratifying convention of 1788 represented Harrison County in the Virginia General Assembly, 1785-90, 1798-1811, and 1814-15 (Swem and Williams. Register, 420).], I can scarcely tell how it happened I was taken by surprise, yielding to the wishes of the People I forgot my condition and every thing that forbade my going to the Assembly.  I was in hopes that the Office vacated by Mr. Nelson would have been tendered me and thereby I should have been extricated from the dilemma.  Your letter disappoints that hope -- it is all we have heard on the subject, and do not even conjecture who is sent from the land of Talents and illumination to enlighten us miserable backwoodsmen, who cannot furnish one Man to fill a local office amongst us.  I care not who he is I will oppose his being confirmed by the Legislature, And if we are conquered--for in this at least we are united.  We will make an effort to break the chains of servitude rivetted by the wise men of the East.  Thank God they can not deprive me of popularity here and while my tongue and pen can urge any thing in the cause of our poor despised country, I will pourtray the condition we are reduced to: and risque every thing to vindicate our rights.  Forgive me my friend for my warmth; it is monstrous injustice to reduce a district of 50,000 inhabitants abounding as all admit in eminent Lawyers: to the degradation of sending a Judge to us over our heads; of mediocre talents and totally ignorant of the great principles involved in our litigations: as much so, as to send a mere land Lawyer to plead Admiralty causes in the maritime districts.  I write somewhat at hazard perhaps some one of our Lawyers is appointed; if so I acquiesce--we have several in whose judgment I can confide and I agree to the appointment of either.  But if he is selected from abroad all I have written I persist in; and should it lead to an open rupture be it so, the Backwoodsmen are not in fault, they feel the wrongs heaped upon them and want only a rallying point to redress them."  John G. Jackson to James Madison, Clarksburg, 19 April 1811, in The Papers of James Madison, Presidential Series Volume 3.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Virginia" geog_id="vas">
				<sub_unit type="District" name="One" geog_id="null">
					<sub_unit type="County" name="Brooke" geog_id="vas_brooke">
						<result candidate_ref="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00620" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
					<sub_unit type="County" name="Harrison" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00620" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
					<sub_unit type="County" name="Monongalia" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" vote="254" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" vote="344" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00620" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
					<sub_unit type="County" name="Ohio" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" vote="233" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" vote="101" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00620" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
					<sub_unit type="County" name="Randolph" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00620" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
					<sub_unit type="County" name="Wood" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.00620" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<note resp="Philip Lampi">"In Wood county, all the votes given in were for Mr. M'Kinley...Nat. Intel."  United States' Gazette (Philadelphia, PA).  April 27, 1811.</note>
						<note resp="Philip Lampi">"~ In Wood, Mr. McKinley had all the votes that were given in."  The Enquirer (Richmond, VA).  April 30, 1811.</note>
					</sub_unit>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role></office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24396">Muskingum Messenger (Zanesville, OH).  April 13, 1811.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24368">National Intelligencer (Washington, DC).  April 25, 1811.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24365">United States' Gazette (Philadelphia, PA).  April 27, 1811.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24378">The Enquirer (Richmond, VA).  April 30, 1811.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24386">New-York Herald (New York, NY).  May 1, 1811.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24387">The Supporter (Chillicothe, OH).  May 4, 1811.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24394">The Reporter (Washington, PA).  May 6, 1811.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24380">The Enquirer (Richmond, VA).  May 10, 1811.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24389">Fayette and Greene Spectator (Uniontown, PA).  May 16, 1811.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24387">New-York Herald (New York, NY).  May 18, 1811.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24354">Norfolk Gazette and Publick Ledger (Norfolk, VA).  May 24, 1811.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24363">Poulson's American Daily Advertiser (Philadelphia, PA).  May 27, 1811.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24375">The Virginia Argus (Richmond, VA).  May 27, 1811.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.24359">Norfolk Gazette and Publick Ledger (Norfolk, VA).  April 28, 1813.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Mattern, David B., J. C. A. Stagg, Jeanne K. Cross and Susan Holbrook Perdue, ed.  The Papers of James Madison, Presidential Series.  Vol. 3.  Charlottesville, VA: University of Virginia Press, 1996.  274-275.</reference>
</election_record>
