<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<election_record xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" label="New York 1813 U.S. Senate, Ballot 2" type="Legislative" iteration="Second Ballot" date="1813" election_id="ny.ussenate2.1813" handle="10427/25571" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
   <office name="U.S. Senate" office_id="ON127" scope="Federal">
      <role title="U.S. Senator" scope="State">
        <ballot>
           <candidate name="Rufus King" name_id="KR0003" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="1"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
           <candidate name="James W. Wilkin" name_id="WJ0459" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="2"/>
           <candidate name="blank" name_id="null" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="3"/>
        </ballot>
        <overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2013-05-24">
           <candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="68" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
           <candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="61" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
           <candidate_summary candidate_ref="3" vote_total="3" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
           <reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09898" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
           <note resp="Philip Lampi">Since the Assembly chose Rufus King for U.S. Senator and the Senate chose James W. Wilkin, a joint ballot of the two houses became necessary.</note>
           <note resp="Philip Lampi">"The two houses not agreeing, both met and went into joint ballot, when Rufus King had 68 votes, James W. Wilkin had 61, and 3 blanks, giving Mr. King a majority of 7 votes over J.W. Wilkin. Four of the Senate were absent."  New-York Spectator (New York, NY).  February 6, 1813.</note>
           <note resp="Philip Lampi">"The Hon. Rufus King was thereupon declared to be duly elected to represent this state in the Senate of the United States for six years from the 4th day of March next. Mr. King is the first federalist who has been elected to represent this state in the Senate of the United States since the year 1803; and it is a subject of the most sincere and heartfelt congratulation to every federalist and friend to peace, not only in this state, but in the United States, that a patriot and statesman of Mr. King's high standing should at this time be elected to fill this important station in the Federal Senate."  The Albany Gazette (Albany, NY).  February 4, 1813.</note>
           <note resp="Philip Lampi">"From The Albany Argus (Albany, NY). United States Senator -- On Tuesday last, the Legislature of this state proceeded to elect, by joint ballot, a Senator, to represent this state in the Senate of the United States for six years from the 4th of March next, in the place of Gen. SMITH. On counting the ballots, there appeared, For Rufus King, 68 votes; James W. Wilkin, 61 do.; Blank ballots, 3.  As this result is very different from what the known ascendancy of republican strangth in our Legislature led many to expect, it may not be amiss to state in detail some of the circumstances which preceded this extraordinary result; a result calculated to fix a stigma upon the republican character of our state, and to defeat the wishes of the people; a majority of whom, as indicated by their representatives in the legislature, are republican. We cheerfully yield to our opponents all the honor they can derive from the aid of duplicity.  The house assembly is composed of 112 members; the Senate consists of 32; total 144. Of this number, 127 were in their seats, and voted on the nomination in their respective houses, as follows: "In Senate, Wilkin 17, King 8, Smith 3, Total, 28. Assembly, Wilkin 44, King 55, Total 99. [vote totals] Wilkin 61, King 63, Smith 3, Total 127.  revious to the vote being taken on joint ballot, two additional senators and three members of assembly, all republicans entered and took their seats, and by their votes swelled the aggregate number to 122. This, according to ordinary calculations, ought to have secured to Gen. Wilkin a majority of three votes. The result, however, showed, that in this age of political necromancy, our calculations should be bottomed on a surer bases than men's professions. For, from the facts stated, we are compelled to adopt one of two conclusions, viz. either that the five republican members who voted only on joint ballot, voted for Mr. King: or, that Mr. K. was elected by the votes of men who had not only pledged themselves, in caucus, to support Gen. Wilkin, but who had openly nominated him a few moments before. Charity would lead to the latter conclusion, had we not the strongest assurances, that at least four of the five members who last came in, voted for Gen. Wilkin."  National Advocate (New York, NY).  February 9, 1813.</note>
           <note resp="Philip Lampi">"Remarkable coincidence. On the same day that a republican correspondent (whose communication we noticed in our last) predicted in Albany, the election of Rufus King to the United States Senate, Coleman predicted the same event, in his Evening Post, at N. York; and what will appear equally strange to some, the perdiction has been literally verified. How came Coleman to know that certain republicans would vote for Mr. King, unless there had been a pledge given?"  National Advocate (New York, NY).  February 9, 1813.</note>
           <note resp="Philip Lampi">"The Hon. Rufus King was thereupon declared to be duly elected to represent this state in the Senate of the United States for six years from the 4th day of March next. Mr. King is the first federalist who has been elected to represent this state in the Senate of the United States since the year 1803; and it is a subject of the most sincere and heartfelt congratlation to every federalist and friend to peace, not only in this state, but in the United States, that a patriot and statesman of Mr. King's high standing should at this time be elected to fill this important station in the Federal Senate."  The Albany Gazette (Albany, NY).  February 4, 1813.</note>
        </overview>
        <admin_unit type="State" name="New York" geog_id="null">
           <sub_unit type="null" name="Assembly and Senate" geog_id="null">
              <result candidate_ref="1" vote="68" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
              <result candidate_ref="2" vote="61" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
              <result candidate_ref="3" vote="3" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
              <reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09898" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
           </sub_unit>
        </admin_unit>
      </role>
   </office>
   <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Journal of the New York Assembly, 1813.  127-129.</reference>
   <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Journal of the New York State Senate, 1813.  81-83.</reference>
   <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Albany Gazette (Albany, NY).  February 4, 1813.</reference>
   <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Lansingburgh Gazette (Lansingburgh, NY).  February 9, 1813.</reference>
   <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09898">New-York Spectator (New York, NY).  February 6, 1813.</reference>
   <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">National Advocate (New York, NY).  February 9, 1813.</reference>
   <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Orange County Patriot; or, the Spirit of Seventy-Six (Goshen, NY).  February 9, 1813.</reference>
   <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Geneva Gazette (Geneva, NY).  February 17, 1813.</reference>
</election_record>
