<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record label="New Jersey 1802 Governor" type="Legislative" iteration="First Ballot" date="1802-10" election_id="nj.governor.1802" handle="10427/20201" xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="Governor" office_id="ON060" scope="State">
		<role title="Governor" scope="State">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="Richard Stockton" name_id="SR0121" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="1"/>
				<candidate name="Joseph Bloomfield" name_id="BJ0589" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="2"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2013-06-20">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="26" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="26" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"On Tuesday last the Members of the Legislature from the several Counties of this state, convened at the State-House in this city. ... On counting the votes for Governor, there appeared: For Joseph Bloomfield, 26. For Richard Stockton, 26. Consequently no choice was made. ... On Friday, a motion was made in the House of Assembly, by a Republican Member, that a message be sent to Council informing that body that the House were ready to go into a Joint-Meeting for the purpose of appointing a Governor and a Chief Justice. This motion was opposed by the Federal party in the House; and was defeated by their negativing the previous question. From present appearances, therefore, there is little room to expect that a Governor will be appointed this year.--In such case, the Vice-President [of the Council] is invested by the 8th section of the Constitution of New-Jersey with all the powers and attributes which attach to the office of Governor.--As the Vice-President is an inflexible Republican; and as the appointment of Senator, if not made by Joint-Meeting, will devolve upon him; the Republicans can lose nothing by the obstinacy of their opponents, but the pleasure of re-appointing their present Governor.--While any injury of inconvenience which may accrue to the state or to individuals from the want of a Governor, will be justly chargeable to the Federal party, who, without strength sufficient to appoint another, in the first instance prevented the re-appointment of the present Governor, and in the second refused even to allow an opportunity of making a choice."  The True American (Trenton, NJ).  November 1, 1802.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Extract of a letter from Trenton, to a Gentleman in this city, dated October 28, 1802. 'It is now well ascertained, this state is to go without a Governor. The business was fully tried this afternoon in joint meeting: when the votes were equally divided viz. 26 for Mr. Bloomfield, and the same number (26) for R. Stockton, Esquire. It is decidedly understood, that neither Party will yield; of course, there cannot be an Election.'"  The Intelligencer, and Weekly Advertiser (Lancaster, PA).  November 2, 1802.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Each having an equal number of votes, there was consequently no Governor chosen. The same division appeared on the question for electing a Senator .... The joint-meeting then broke up, without making a single appointment."  The Centinel of Freedom (Newark, NJ).  November 2, 1802.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="New Jersey" geog_id="null">
				<sub_unit type="null" name="In convention" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="26" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="26" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The True American (Trenton, NJ).  November 1, 1802.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Centinel of Freedom (Newark, NJ).  November 2, 1802.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Intelligencer, and Weekly Advertiser (Lancaster, PA).  November 2, 1802.</reference>
</election_record>
