<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record label="Virginia 1804 Electoral College, Special" type="Special" iteration="First Ballot" date="1804-12" election_id="va.president.special.1804" handle="10427/65101" xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="Electoral College" office_id="ON056" scope="Federal">
		<role title="Elector" scope="State">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="Lemuel Reddick" name_id="RL0045" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="1"/>
				<candidate name="Richard Brooke" name_id="BR0043" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="2"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2011-08-01">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"The speaker laid before the house a letter from the honorable George Wythe, chairman of the electoral body of this state, for the choice of president and vice president of the United States, covering a resolution of that body, directing their chairman to inform the legislature, by letter addressed to the speaker of each house, that on this day (Tuesday the 4th of December, 1804,) at three o'clock, two of the electors, to wit -- Larkin Smith, of King and Queen and Richard Evers Lee, of Norfolk Borough, did not appear, and are not at present in the city of Richmond. On Motion, Resolved, That this house will immediately proceed by joint ballot with the Senate, to the choice of two electors, to supply the vacancies resulting from the non attendance, at three o'clock in the afternoon of this day, of Richard E. Lee and Larkin Smith, elected by the people, pursuant to an act, entitled, 'An act, to amend an act, entitled an act, to amend an act, entitled an act for appointing electors to choose a president and vice president of the United States.' Ordered,That Mr. Johnston do carry the said resolution to the senate and desire their concurrance. Resolved, That the operation of that rule of this house, which directs that in all cases of balloting, one vacancy only shall be filled or created at a time, be suspended during the ensuing election of electors. A message from the senate by Mr. Robb.  Mr. Speaker -- The senate have agreed to the resolution to proceed immediately by joint ballot, to the choice of electors to supply the vacancies occasioned by the non attendance of those elected pursuant to an act...'To amend an act...for appointing electors to choose a president and vice president of the U. States.' The house then proceeded, according to order, to the choice of two electors, to supply the place of the absentees. And the members having prepared tickets, with the names of the persons to be balloted for, and deposited the same in the ballot boxes, Messrs....were named a committee to meet a committee from the Senate, and jointly with them examine the ballots, and report to the house, on whom a majority of votes should fall. The committee then withdrew, and after some time returned into the house, and Mr. harrison reported that the committee had, according to order, met a committee from the Senate, and jointly with them examined the ballots and had found a majority of the whole number of votes in favor of Mr. Lemuel Riddick, of Nansemond, and Mr. Richard Brooke, of King and Queen."</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">In spite of this election, all historical records indicate that Richard E. Lee and Larkin Smith did cast their votes in the Electoral College.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Virginia" geog_id="vas">
				<sub_unit type="null" name="Senate" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
				<sub_unit type="null" name="House of Delegates" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Journal of the Virginia House of Delegates, 1804.  7, 8.</reference>
</election_record>
