<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" label="Massachusetts 1804 Speaker of the House" type="Legislative" iteration="First Ballot" date="1804" election_id="ma.housespeaker.1804" handle="10427/28089" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="Speaker of the House" office_id="ON104" scope="State">
		<role title="Speaker of the House" scope="State">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="Harrison G. Otis" name_id="OH0028" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="1"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="Perez Morton" name_id="MP0042" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="2"/>
				<candidate name="scattering" name_id="null" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="3"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2014-10-13">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="129" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="103" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="3" vote_total="3" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10451" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10452" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"There were three scattering votes, two of them given by the candidates, and one by mistake."  Columbian Centinel and Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  June 2, 1804.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">The whole number of votes was 235; necessary to make a choice, 118.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"In the House, the vote for Speaker and Clerk, shew, that the Federal Majority was TWENTY-SIX:--But we can assure the public, that this is not the whole Federal Majority:--We know of nearly twenty Federalists who have been elected; and who have from unavoidable circumstances been prevented attending at the opening of the session.--Of them, are Colonel LITTLE, of Newbury; Col. PORTER, of Hadley; Mr. CHURCH, of Sunderland; Mr. PHELPS, of Granville; Mr. GARDNER, of South Brimfield; Mr. HALE, of Long-meadow; Mr. BOWERS, of Somerset; Mr. HOWE, of Rutland; Mr. MARSH, of Douglas; Mr. PARRIS, of Heron; Col. FOXCRAFT, of New-Gloucester; Mr. M'COBB, of Boothbay; Mr. HASTINGS, of Hardwick; Mr. OAKMAN, of Pittston; Mr. DUNING, of Harpswell; Mr. WHITNEY, of Westminster; and several others. We state, as certain, that the Federal Majority of the members chosen, exceeds Thirty. On the other hand, nearly the intire strength of the democrats was on the ground.--We cannot enumerate more than ten or twelve that were absent;--They had been notified to attend early, by the Chronicle.--In addition to this, circulars were sent to the individual members.--We have seen one of them, sent, by mistake, to a federal member; and shall endeavor to obtain his permission to present the public with the curious mandamus."  Columbian Centinel and Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  June 2, 1804.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"The federal majority is smaller in the House of Representatives this year than it was the last; yet it seems not certain from this, that the federal paty has declined in the State; for some towns have this year sent representatives which did not last; and others, which did last year, have neglected to this; so that the casual variation from year to year does not form a perfect criterion of change in the political sentiments of the people. It has been understood, that the Democrats have this year made uncommon exertions to bring about a representation as full as their numbers and the law would allow; whereas the Boston Gazette asserts, on the other hand, that it can reckon seventy federal towns that have not this year exercised their privilege of sending Representatives; and even the Chronicle allows, that though the federal candidate for the Speaker's chair had a smaller majority, yet that he had actually more votes, than he had last year.--On the whole, we believe there is good reason to say, that federalism is as strong as ever in Massachusetts."  Salem Gazette (Salem, MA).  June 1, 1804.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Massachusetts" geog_id="null">
				<sub_unit type="null" name="House of Representatives" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="129" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="103" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="3" vote="3" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10451" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10452" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Salem Gazette (Salem, MA).  June 1, 1804.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10451">Columbian Centinel and Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  June 2, 1804.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Democrat (Boston, MA).  June 2, 1804.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10452">American Citizen (New York, NY).  June 6, 1804.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10452">The Virginia Argus (Richmond, VA).  June 13, 1804.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10452">Republican Star or Eastern Shore General Advertiser (Easton, MD).  June 19, 1804.</reference>
</election_record>
