<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" label="Massachusetts 1804 House of Representatives, Salem" type="General" iteration="First Ballot" date="1804-05" election_id="ma.statelegislature.salem.1804" handle="10427/27886" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="House of Representatives" office_id="ON064" scope="State">
		<role title="State Representative" scope="Town">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="William Cleveland" name_id="CW0072" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="1"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="John Hathorne" name_id="HJ0293" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="2"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="John Southwick" name_id="SJ0389" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="3"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="William Gray, Jr." name_id="GW0055" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="4"/>
				<candidate name="Nathaniel Bowditch" name_id="BN0046" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="5"/>
				<candidate name="Jonathan Waldo" name_id="WJ0275" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="6"/>
				<candidate name="scattering" name_id="null" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="7"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2014-10-17">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="534" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="533" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="3" vote_total="533" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="4" vote_total="456" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="5" vote_total="454" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="6" vote_total="444" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="7" vote_total="5" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.03460" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.03461" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"[It was our intention to have given the result of the late unprecedentedly contested election, without any comments, but we feel that we have no right to disregard the wishes of some of our best friends. We therefore insert the following.] The election in this town for Representatives to the General Court was held on Tuesday the 15th inst. The contest between the two great political parties which divide this State was ardent. Never had the federalists done so much, and never had they less cause for boasting. They have been beaten, and fairly and honorably beaten--and although they brought forward Mr. WM. GRAY, jr. the greatest and richest merchant in the United States, at the head of their ticket, they have now found that, wealth, united with great personal influence, has weighed only as the dust of the balance. Republicans will never support men known to be opposed to systems and measures they deem invaluable. It is to pure principles they adhere. It is to 'law and order,' contrasted to federal confusion and wild uproar, the republicans of Salem will wlways cling, as to the last and best hope of man. The poll was opened at 11, and closed at 5 o'clock--when the following result of the election was declared ...Republican majority, upon an average, 80."  Salem Register (Salem, MA).  May 17, 1804.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"On Tuesday last, this town made choice of its Representatives, and the Antifederalists once more triumphed. The following was the state of the poll at its close ... For those who know the different men composing the two lists, comment is unnecessary. Passion and party spirit aside, there can be no doubt but those whom the federalists supported would have been the choice of the people, in preference to the others. As to the talk in the Register, to make us believe that Mr. Gray, Maj. Waldo and Mr. Bowditch have some desperate plan in their minds hostile to our liberties, and would oppose themselves to 'systems and measures which the people deem invaluable;' and that on Col. Hathorne, Mr. Cleveland and Master Southwick depend 'the last and best hope of man'--no sober person can pay any regard to it. The talents of Col. Hathorne were never suspected of being of that peculiar kind, that would lead this last, best hope of man to seek a refuge in them. As to Mr. Cleveland, it is impossible, from his inert life, that he can feel that concern for the interests of the town, which a man engaged in active business does: his notions in legislation, therefore, instead of being the fruit of experience, must be spun from his own theoretic brain. Master Southwick, immured in a school of fifty or sixty boys from morning till night, may be very expert at vulgar fractions, but we cannot think he knows much of political arithmetic. Indeed, though the Demos have ungratefully cast by Major Sprague, to introduce another in his stead, we do not imagine they have greatly improved their representation; nor do we think the last best hope of man has much to hope even from the united powers of the three--With much deference, however, be it said."  Salem Gazette (Salem, MA).  May 18, 1804.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Massachusetts" geog_id="null">
				<sub_unit type="Town" name="Salem" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="534" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="533" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="3" vote="533" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="4" vote="456" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="5" vote="454" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="6" vote="444" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.03460" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.03461" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Salem Register (Salem, MA).  May 17, 1804.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.03461">The Salem Gazette (Salem, MA).  May 18, 1804.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.03460">The Democrat (Boston, MA).  May 19, 1804.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Independent Chronicle (Boston, MA).  May 24, 1804.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Pittsfield Sun (Pittsfield, MA).  May 28, 1804.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Independent Chronicle (Boston, MA).  June 4, 1804.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Republican Spy (Springfield, MA).  June 11, 1804.</reference>
</election_record>
