<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" label="Pennsylvania 1806 U.S. Senate, Ballot 3" type="Legislative" iteration="Third Ballot" date="1806-12" election_id="pa.us.senator.1806" handle="10427/61708" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="U.S. Senate" office_id="ON127" scope="Federal">
		<role title="U.S. Senator" scope="State">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="Andrew Gregg" name_id="GA0060" affiliation="Constitutionalist" affiliation_id="A07" candidate_num="1"/>
				<candidate name="John Steele" name_id="SJ0998" affiliation="Democrat" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="2"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2012-05-25">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="54" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="54" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09986" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09987" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09988" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09989" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"On Tuesday last, both Branches of the Legislature met in the Representatives chamber, to elect a Senator for this state in the Senate of the United States." The Intelligencer, and Weekly Advertiser (Lancaster, PA).  December 16, 1806.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"It requiring a majority of the whole members present to make a choice, the vote was again taken, and the result the same as before. Neither of the candidates having a majority of votes, and being a tie, the vote was to take three several times, and the issue finally the same. Upon which the meeting adjourned until Tuesday the 16th inst...Mr. Poe and Mr. Rankin (both Snyderites) voted for Mr. Gregg~ Mewhorter and Wertz, of the senate, both absent."Kline's Carlisle Weekly Gazette (Carlisle, PA).  December 19, 1806.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">A third trial served only to prove the firmness of the opposition-all the members adhering to their former votes. -it was agreed to adjourn the meeting until Tuesday next at 12 o'clock." The True American and Commercial Advertiser (Philadelphia, PA).  December 15, 1806.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"The real fight came over the choice of a United States Senator to succeed George Logan.  The Federalists and Quids were determined to back Andrew Gregg, Congressman from Centre County, who had been defeated for re-election in October.  At the Democratic caucus on December 4, 1806, John Thompson, a member of the Philadelphia County delegation, warmly supported the nomination of Leib.  He praised his services and talents and argued that the commercial interests of Philadelphia were entitled to a representative since the agricultural interest was already represented by Samuel Maclay.  At a second caucus on the following day a vote was taken; and John Steele, former State Senator from Lancaster County, was chosen over Leibe by 37 votes to nine.  The two houses met in joint session on December 9, 1806, and balloted three times.  On each ballot Steele and Gregg were tied with 54 votes apiece.  On this occasion two Quid Senators were absent; and a vacancy existed in the Philadelphia County delegation due to the death of George S. Bensell a Democrat, whose successor had not then been chosen.  It seemed that Gregg was assured of victory when the whole membership was present.  Despite this appearance, the Democrats actually outnumbered the Quids and Federalists; but two of them had voted for Gregg for personal reasons.  James Poe, Senator from Franklin County, was Gregg's brother-in-law; and William Rankin, Representative from Centre County, was his neighbor.  These two were persuaded by the Democrats to vote for a postponement of the election till January.  This, when the two houses held a second session on December 16, 1806, although the two absent Quids were now present, it was voted 56-54 to adjourn until January 13, 1807."  Higginbotham, Sanford W.  The Keystone in the Democratic Arch: Pennsylvania Politics, 1800-1816.  Philadelphia: Pennyslvania Historical and Museum Commission, 1952. 131.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Pennsylvania" geog_id="null">
				<sub_unit type="null" name="General Assembly" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="54" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="54" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<sub_unit type="null" name="House of Representatives" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" vote="43" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" vote="42" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09987" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09988" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
					<sub_unit type="null" name="State Senate" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" vote="11" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" vote="12" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09987" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09988" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09986">The True American and Commercial Advertiser (Philadelphia, PA).  December 11, 1806.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09987">The True American and Commercial Advertiser (Philadelphia, PA).  December 15, 1806.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09989">The Intelligencer, and Weekly Advertiser (Lancaster, PA).  December 16, 1806.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09988">Kline's Carlisle Weekly Gazette (Carlisle, PA).  December 19, 1806.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Higginbotham, Sanford W.  The Keystone in the Democratic Arch: Pennsylvania Politics, 1800-1816.  Philadelphia: Pennyslvania Historical and Museum Commission, 1952. 131.</reference>
</election_record>
