<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<election_record xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" label="Vermont 1813 Lieutenant Governor, Ballot 3" type="Legislative" iteration="Third Ballot" date="1813" election_id="vt.ltgovernor3.1813" handle="10427/78795" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
    <office name="Lieutenant Governor" office_id="ON073" scope="State">
        <role title="Lieutenant Governor" scope="State">
            <ballot>
                <candidate name="William Chamberlain" name_id="CW0352" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="1"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
                <candidate name="Paul Brigham" name_id="BP0101" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="2"/>
            </ballot>
            <overview status="null" modified="2014-08-14">
                <candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="112" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
                <candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="111" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
                <note resp="Philip Lampi">The legislature being evenly divided between Federalists and Republicans, the second ballot for lieutenant governor resulted in a tie. One of the Republican legislators, Judge Bradford Kinne, was ill and returned to his lodgings, expecting to return to cast a vote on the third ballot. However, the vote was held in his absence and William Chamberlain was elected lieutenant governor.</note>
                <note resp="Philip Lampi">"From the Rutland Vermont Herald (Rutland, VT). 'FROM OUR ATTENTIVE CORRESPONDENT.  Montpelier, 24th.  Oct.  1813. ... Another ballot took place; but one of the republicans being sick, had gone out in the interim, to his boarding house, and before he could return the votes were counted, and Chamberlain declared elected by a majority of one, to wit, one hundred and twelve to 111.'" The Democratic Press (Philadelphia, PA), November 14, The Alexandria Herald (Alexandria, VA), November 17, 1813.</note>
                <note resp="Philip Lampi">"Before a second ballot could be had, one of the republican members, (Mr. Kenne) from extreme illness, and who had been brought into the house, at his own request, to vote for governor, was obliged to retire ; and on the ballots being taken, it appeared that Mr. Chamberlin had a majority of one." Rutland Vermont Herald (Rutland, VT), October 26, 1813.</note>
                <note resp="Philip Lampi">"Extracts of a letter to the Editor of the Star, dated Montpelier, Saturday Evening, October, 23d, 1813 ... 'On Thursday the 21st the two houses met in joint committee for the purpose of electing a Governor and Lt. Governor. ... On the first ballot for Lieut. Governor, it appeared that there were 112 votes for Paul Brigham, and 112 votes for Wm. Chamberlain. Before it was ascertained how the votes stood, Judge Kinney, of Plainfield, being extremely unwell, and supposing that the election would terminate in the same way as that for Governor, left the house and returned to his lodgings. On the second ballot it apperaed that Wm. Chamberlain had 112 votes and Paul Brigham 111, and before Judge Kinney could return to the house (although he had started for tht purpose) the election was declared in favor of Wm. Chamberlain.'" North Star (Danville, VT).  October 30, 1813.</note>
                <note resp="Philip Lampi">"Political. FROM THE WATCHMAN. ELECTION, No. II. ... On the first ballot for Lieut. Governor, each candidate had 112 votes. The ballots being again taken, it appeared that Judge Kinne, who was sick, had left the house. After waiting some time, for his return, the committee was informed, that he was too far exhausted to appear in the house, and the ballots being found to be 112 for the Hon. WILLIAM CHAMBERLIN, and 111 for his honor Paul Brigham, the former was proclaimed as duly elected ... An Eye and Ear Witness." The Washingtonian (Windsor, VT), November 8, 1813." </note>
            </overview>
            <admin_unit type="State" name="Vermont" geog_id="null">
                <sub_unit type="null" name="General Assembly" geog_id="null">
                    <result candidate_ref="1" vote="112" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
                    <result candidate_ref="2" vote="111" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
                    <sub_unit type="null" name="House of Representatives" geog_id="null">
                        <result candidate_ref="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
                        <result candidate_ref="2" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
                    </sub_unit>
                    <sub_unit type="null" name="Council" geog_id="null">
                        <result candidate_ref="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
                        <result candidate_ref="2" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
                    </sub_unit>
                </sub_unit>
            </admin_unit>
        </role>
    </office>
    <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Rutland Vermont Herald (Rutland, VT).  October 26, 1813.</reference>
    <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">North Star (Danville, VT).  October 30, 1813.</reference>
    <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Washingtonian (Windsor, VT).  November 8, 1813.</reference>
    <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">North Star (Danville, VT).  November 11, 1813.</reference>
    <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Democratic Press (Philadelphia, PA).  November 14, 1813.</reference>
    <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Alexandria Herald (Alexandria, VA).  November 17, 1813.</reference>
    <reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Degree, Kenneth A.  "Impasse! Vermont's 1813 Legislative Session."  Vermont History.  78, no. 2. (Summer/Fall 2010).  151-180.</reference>
</election_record>

