<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record label="Massachusetts 1803 U.S. Senate, Ballot 4" type="Legislative" iteration="Fourth Ballot" date="1803-02" election_id="ma.ussenator4.1803" handle="10427/27472" xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="U.S. Senate" office_id="ON127" scope="Federal">
		<role title="U.S. Senator" scope="State">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="John Quincy Adams" name_id="AJ0043" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="1"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="Thompson J. Skinner" name_id="ST0101" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="2"/>
				<candidate name="Nicholas Tillinghast" name_id="TN0022" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="3"/>
				<candidate name="Timothy Pickering" name_id="PT0078" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="4"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2014-09-29">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="105" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="70" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="3" vote_total="9" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="4" vote_total="6" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"On Thursday, the choice of a Senator to represent this State in the Senate of the United States, in the room of the Hon. JONATHAN MASON, whose term of service expires next month, came on in the House of Representatives. It was previously known that Mr. MASON declined being a candidate; and of near twenty names which were placed on the nomination list, the Federal Republicans generally appeared to have selected two; both of whom have been the objects of democratic persecution--the Hon. TIMOTHY PICKERING, late Secretary of State, and the Hon. JOHN QUINCY ADAMS, late Minister Plenipotenitary of the United States, to the Court of Berlin. When circumstances place two such men as candidates for the same office, it is not an easy task to give a preference. ON THE FOURTH TRIAL, The votes were 171--86 a choice ... The Hon. JOHN QUINCY ADAMS was therefore declared to be chosen on the part of the House; and sent up to the Senate for concurrence. The Senate have assigned Tuesday next, 12 o'clock, for coming to a choice on their part."  Columbian Centinel. Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  February 5, 1803.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"This day at 12 o'clock, the house proceeded agreeably to assignment to ballot for a person to represent this commonwealth in the senate of the United States, vice Mr. Mason, whose term of service expires with the third of March next, and who declined being a candidate for a new election. There were four trials ... The hon. John Quincy Adams, was declared to be chosen by the house, and a message sent to the senate with the information. Where he was also elected."  Republican Star or Eastern Shore General Advertiser (Easton, MD).  March 1, 1803.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"It is clear by the votes that Pickering was the candidate contemplated [by the Federalists]: for J.Q. Adams had but ten on the first trial, and six the second. After two unsuccessful attempts to carry their favorite, they reluctantly gave Mr. Adams a slight support; for they could not consolidate this interest father than to obtain a bare majority. Observing the strength of the Republicans to continue stable in every trial, they began to be fearful of the event; and lest Mr. Skinner should get a majority on another trial, they tho't fit to join issue in Mr. Adams. This appeared to many spectators to be the true state of the business."  The Independent Chronicle (Boston, MA).  February 7, 1803.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"SENATOR OF THE UNITED STATES. YESTERDAY the Senate of this Commonwealth proceeded to the choice of a Senator of the United States; when the Hon. JOHN QUINCY ADAMS Was chosen, in concurrence with the House.--Of 26 votes, Mr. ADAMS had 19."  Columbian Centinel. Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  February 9, 1803.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">The Frederick-Town Herald (Fredericktown, MD): "On Tuesday the 7th. ult. the Senate of the commonwealth of Massachusetts proceeded to the choice of a Senator of the United States, when the Hon. John Quincy Adams was chosen in concurrence with the house. Of 26 votes, Mr. Adams had 19."  Frederick-Town Herald (Fredericktown, MD).  March 5, 1803.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Massachusetts" geog_id="null">
				<sub_unit type="null" name="House of Representatives" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="86" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="70" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="3" vote="9" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="4" vote="6" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09783" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
				<sub_unit type="null" name="State Senate" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="19" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09784" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Columbian Centinel. Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  February 5, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Independent Chronicle (Boston, MA).  February 7, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Columbian Centinel. Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  February 9, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Hampshire Gazette (Northampton, MA).  February 9, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Boston Gazette (Boston, MA).  February 10, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09783">Republican Star or Eastern Shore General Advertiser (Easton, MD).  March 1, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09784">Frederick-Town Herald (Fredericktown, MD).  March 5, 1803.</reference>
</election_record>
