<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" label="Massachusetts 1803 U.S. Senate, Special, Ballot 2" type="Special" iteration="Second Ballot" date="1803" election_id="ma.ussenate.special.housevote2.1803" handle="10427/27790" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="U.S. Senate" office_id="ON127" scope="Federal">
		<role title="U.S. Senator" scope="State">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="Timothy Pickering" name_id="PT0078" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="1"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="Thompson Skinner" name_id="ST0101" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="2"/>
				<candidate name="Nicholas Tillinghast" name_id="TN0022" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="3"/>
				<candidate name="Henry Knox" name_id="KH0025" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="4"/>
				<candidate name="Benjamin Pickman" name_id="PB0029" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="5"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2014-09-29">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="76" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="52" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="3" vote_total="3" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="4" vote_total="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="5" vote_total="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Massachusetts" geog_id="null">
				<sub_unit type="null" name="House of Representatives" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="59" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="52" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="3" vote="3" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="4" vote="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="5" vote="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09785" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Yesterday, agreeably to previous assignment, the H. of R. proceeded to the choice, and in concurrence with the Senate, the Hon. Timothy Pickering was elected, for two years after this day ... On the second trial, the whole number 116, necessary to a choice 59 ... Thus it appears that the Hon. Messrs. Pickering and Adams have been chosen into the Senate of the U. States, by the majority of a single vote each; although pushed forward by all the remaining efforts of Massachusetts' federalism. It is clearly to be discovered, by an examination of the various votes in the house, that neither of these gentlemen were the objects of choice with an actual majority of the electors; had not peculiar circumstances operated to give them an election. The fact unquestionably is, that the leaders of federalism in the Legislature were pledged to the Essex Junto to promote Mr. Pickering, by all practicable means; and upon principles of reciprocity, the gentlemen of Essex were bound to the federalists, to support Mr. Adams--and they must certainly have the credit of having faithfully fulfilled their bargains: for they spared no pains to bring the moderate federalists into measures which were naturally so repugnant to their feelings. That they should have succeeded so completely is not very strange, when we contemplate the united weight of two so influential and active parties, as those which have been mentioned, whenever they can be brought to act in even forced concert! The result of the votes, however, furnishes us with one certain and consoling reflection--that Massachusetts Federalism, with all her united and adventitious forces, has nothing to spare; and that though she has in this instance husbanded her means to the best advantage, her votaries will not probably soon be able again to cover her nakedness by the union of her scattered shreds."  The Independent Chronicle (Boston, MA).  March 3, 1803.</note>
					<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Glorious News for the Essex Junto! The H-o-n-o-r-a-b-l-e Timothy Pickering, Esq. after being a Candidate half a dozen times, is at last chosen a Senator from this State to the United States, in the room of Dwight Foster, Esq. who resigned--out of complaisance to Timmy. Mr. P. deserves credit for his indefatigability in standing so long as a Candidate. How consoling will this news be to the ex-President, and his Heir Apparent!"  Salem Register (Salem, MA).  March 3, 1803.</note>
					<note resp="Philip Lampi">"On Tuesday last, the Senate of this Commonwealth came to the choice of a Senator of the U. States, in the room of the Hon. Dwight Foster, esq. resigned. Gen. Skinner was the Republican, and the Honorable Timothy Pickering, late Secretary of State, the Federal candidate. The whole number of votes was 27, of which Mr. Pickering had 17, and was chosen!--Messrs. Hitchborn, Hull, Hildreth and Coffin, (of Nantucket) all Republicans, were absent."  The Independent Chronicle (Boston, MA).  March 3, 1803.</note>
				</sub_unit>
				<sub_unit type="null" name="State Senate" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="17" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Boston Gazette (Boston, MA).  March 3, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Independent Chronicle (Boston, MA).  March 3, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Salem Register (Salem, MA).  March 3, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">New-England Palladium (Boston, MA).  March 4, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Salem Gazette (Salem, MA).  March 4, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Columbian Centinel. Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  March 5, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09785">The Bee (Hudson, NY).  March 15, 1803.</reference>
</election_record>
