<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record label="Virginia 1803 U.S. Senate, Special" type="Special" iteration="First Ballot" date="1803-12" election_id="va.ussenate.special.second.1803" handle="10427/32949" xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="U.S. Senate" office_id="ON127" scope="Federal">
		<role title="U.S. Senator" scope="State">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="Abraham B. Venable" name_id="VA0029" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="1"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2011-07-19">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10191" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10192" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10193" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10194" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10195" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10196" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">Election occurred on December 7. "[Abraham B. Venable] unanimously chosen...Richmond, Dec. 10, 1803. The Hon. Abraham B. Venable was on Wednesday last unanimously elected a Senator of the United States to supply the vacancy occasioned by the death of Stephen T. Mason.  Mr. Taylor, who supplied the place by Executive appointment, declined to serve longer." The Examiner (Richmond, VA), December 10, 1803; and, Columbian Centinel (Boston, MA), December 24, 1803.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Abraham B. Venable, Esquire, was on Wednesday last, unanimously elected by the Legislature of this Commonwealth, a Senator in Congress to supply the vacancy occasioned by the death of General Steven Thompson Mason -- Col. John Taylor, appointed by the Executive, having resigned his seat." The Virginia Argus (Richmond, VA).  December 10, 1803.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Richmond, December 10. The time for which John Taylor was appointed Senator of this state in the Congress of the United States, by the Executive, to supply the vacancy occasioned by the death of Stephen T. Mason having expired, and Mr. Taylor having declined to serve longer, Abraham B. Venable, esq. was on Wednesday last unanimously elected by the General Assembly in the room of Mr. Taylor." Gazette of the United States (Philadelphia, PA).  December 16, 1803.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Petersburg, December 13...Abraham B. Venable,esq. was on Wednesday last, unanimously elected by the legislature of this commonwealth, a senator in Congress to supply the vacancy occasioned by the death of Stevens Thompson Mason -- Col. John Taylor, appointed by the Executive, having resigned his seat in said body." The Palladium (Frankfort, KY).  December 31, 1803.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Abraham B. Venable is unanimously elected by the legislature of Virginia, a Senator in the Congress of the U. States." Political Observatory (Walpole, NH).  December 31, 1803.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Abraham B. Venable has been unanimously chosen by the legislature of Virginia to represent that state in the Senate of the United States, as successor of John Taylor, Esq. whose time had expired and who declined a re-election -- Mr. Taylor filled the seat as successor of Stephens Thompson Mason, Esq. deceased." Connecticut Gazette, and the Commercial Intelligencer (New London, CT), December 28, 1803; and, Raleigh Register, and North-Carolina State Gazette (Raleigh, NC), January 2, 1804.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"John Taylor...appointed to the United States Senate as a Democratic Republican to fill the vacancy caused by the death of Stevens T. Mason and served from June 4 to December 7, 1803, when a successor was elected; was not a candidate for election to fill the vacancy." Biographical Directory of the United States Congress: 1774 - Present.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Abraham Bedford Venable...elected as a Democratic Republican to the United States Senate to fill the vacancy caused by the death of Stevens T. Mason and served from December 7, 1803, to June 7, 1804, when he resigned to become president of the first national bank organized in Virginia." Biographical Directory of the United States Congress: 1774 - Present.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Virginia" geog_id="vas">
				<sub_unit type="null" name="Senate" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
				<sub_unit type="null" name="House of Delegates" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role></office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10195">The Examiner (Richmond, VA).  December 10, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10192">The Virginia Argus (Richmond, VA).  December 10, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10191">Gazette of the United States (Philadelphia, PA).  December 16, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10195">Columbian Centinel and Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  December 24, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10194">Connecticut Gazette, and the Commercial Intelligencer (New London, CT).  December 28, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10193">The Palladium (Frankfort, KY).  December 31, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10196">Political Observatory (Walpole, NH).  December 31, 1803.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10194">Raleigh Register, and North-Carolina State Gazette (Raleigh, NC).  January 2, 1804.</reference>
</election_record>
