<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record label="New Jersey 1807 Referendum, Essex County" type="General" iteration="First Ballot" date="1807" election_id="nj.referendum.essex.1807" handle="10427/68307" xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="Referendum" office_id="ON086" scope="County">
		<role title="Referendum" scope="County">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="Newark" name_id="null" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="1"/>
				<candidate name="Days Hill" name_id="null" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="2"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2013-03-11">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="7666" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="6181" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"By the beginning of the present century it became apparent that not many years could elapse before a new courthouse would be imperatively demanded in Essex County. The people of Elizabethtown, then included in this county, were jealous of the growth of Newark, and ambitious to have the seat of justice located within the limits of their town. Elizabethtown had a preponderating influence in the Board of Freeholders, and here representatives and those controlled by them had steadily resisted the making of repairs upon the old building or the erection (in Newark) of a new one. Elizabethtown was thus the master of the situation. Finally, however, it was agreed to submit the matter of the courthouse location to a vote of the people, for which authority was obtained through a special act of the Legislature. In this election all single women and widows were allowed to vote, only wives says Mr. Atkinson, being placed on a political level with infants and idiots. Neither was there any restriction in regard to color. Seven localities were place in nomination for the site. These were distributed in Newark, Elizabethtown and Days Hill, and the contest was ostensibly between the first and last, Elizabethtowns choice being the latter, which was within its bounds.  Great excitement attended the canvass, the election and the count succeeding it. Mass meeting were held in all parts of the county and the claims of the different localities were urged by a score of orators with a vigor and virulence not transcended even in the hottest of modern political contest. Everybody was enlisted in the war. Such animosity was engendered that it was not safe for Newark people to visit Elizabethtown or those who were active champions of the latter towns claim to enter the boundaries of Newark.  The election, which lasted three days, began at Days Hill, Feb. 10, 1807. During the forenoon the election was believed to be fairly conducted, but in the afternoon illegal voting was commenced, and carried on with the utmost boldness until the close of the polls. Next day the struggle was transferred to the Elizabethtown polls, and there greater dishonesty prevailed than at Days Hill. Next came Newarks chance, and here the corruption was more open and shameless than at either of the other places. As early as one oclock in the morning of the day, big with fate of Newark, the polls were opened at the old courthouse, and the third and conclusive day of the battle was begun. Aaron Munn was judge of the election. The voting had not long been in progress when fraud was resorted to, and carried on in every way known to the ballot-box stuffers of the times. Repeating was resorted to, by many who would in any other cause have scorned such action. Men usually honest seemed lost to all sense of honor, so completely were they carried away by the strife. Women vied with the men, and in some instance surpassed them, in illegal voting. Only a few years ago there were living in Newark two ladies, who, at the time of the election in their teens, voted six times each. Married women, too, indignant, perhaps, at being placed on the same political level as children and idiots, in defiance of the law, cast their ballots. Governor Pennington is said to have escorted to the polls a strapping negress. Men and boys disguised themselves in womens attire, and crowded about the polls to assist in winning the day for Newark. Challenging seems not to have been resorted to. Vehicles of all kinds were pressed into service to transport the voters from one polling place to another, voting at several being as common as voting early and often at one. Spies were sent to Elizabethtown at intervals to see how many more votes were wanted to keep ahead. Men were brought down the river in large gangs to cast their ballots when it was feared that the fight would be lost. The whole transaction was the broadest kind of burlesque and the most flagrant outrage. At the close of the polls victory perched upon the Newark banners, but women suffrage was at an end in New Jersey, for the legislature at its next session passed an act limiting the right to vote to free white male citizens.  .... But after all the election was not a victory for Newark, for the beaten party, crying fraud opposed by every means the building of a new courthouse in Newark, and the matter finally being taken before the Legislature, the election was declared by that body corrupt and illegal, and therefore set aside, greatly to the discomfiture of the Newark people and the joy of the Elizabethtown inhabitants. A very good idea of the amount of fraud in this election can be arrived at by the reflection that the vote at the Newark polls, 5039, was only 961 less than the number of the entire population, three years afterwards. The relative figures of vote and population at Elizabethtown show an equally bad state of affairs."  History of Essex and Hudson Counties, New Jersey.  212-213.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Essex Court House: Agreeably to an act of the Legislature, an election has been held in the county of Essex for a place at which to erect a new Court house and Jail. A number of places were nominated, but two only were voted for, viz. a place between Newark and Springfield, called Days Hill, and the spot on which the present Court house stands, in Newark. A more severe contest probably never took place on such an occasion. Nearly 14,000 ballots were taken in throughout the county, and more than 5000 in the single township of Newark. The following is a statement of the votes in the several townships:"  New-Jersey Journal (Elizabethtown, NJ).  February 17, 1807.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Last Tuesday and Wednesday, the election for fixing on a place to build a Court house and Gaol, was held in the different Townships of the County; and sorry we are to have it to relate, that a more wicked and corrupt scene was never exhibited in this State, or in the United States. Perjury and all it's concomitant evils, were committed, we believe, by persons from whom concerning their respectability in society, we had a right to expect better things; and even professors of religion, and others in civil authority, are implicated in this nefarious measure. Threats, insult, and abuse were offered to civil officers in the exercise of their rights. - our quondam friends of Newark have much of this blame attached to them. - As this daring outrage on our liberties will likely come before a proper tribunal for investigation, we forbear going into particulars; but shall content ourselves with making one remark, that if such scenes of corruption and profligacy is not corrected, it cuts up government by the roots and poisons the very fountain of public security."  The True American (Trenton, NJ).  February 23, 1807.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"The election which took place last week, was the most warm and spirited ever held in the county of Essex, and probably ere witnessed in the state. - For weeks preceding the election, the most indefatigable labor had been spent by each party in organizing for the election. When the tenth of Feb. arrived, every man stood ready at his post, prepared for the combat; every town and village was divided into districts, and men specially appointed to see the electors to the poll. Every nerve was strained by each party to ensure success. - The issue of the election is stated above. On Saturday, when the county clerk proclaimed the majority in favor of Newark, the old court house resounded with the loud and repeated huzzahs of an assembled multitude; every heart beat with joy, every countenance beamed satisfaction and such mutual congratulations we doubt were ever witnessed before. Cannon announced the triumph of Newark and her friends; and in the evening the court house, as well as the town in general, was brilliantly illuminated."  The Centinel of Freedom (Newark, NJ).  February 17, 1807.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="New Jersey" geog_id="null">
				<sub_unit type="County" name="Essex" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="7666" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="6181" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<sub_unit type="Township" name="Acquackanonk" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" vote="1884" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" vote="7" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
					<sub_unit type="Township" name="Caldwell" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" vote="860" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
					<sub_unit type="Township" name="Elizabeth" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" vote="29" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" vote="2257" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
					<sub_unit type="Township" name="Newark" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" vote="4792" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" vote="247" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
					<sub_unit type="Township" name="Rahway" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" vote="50" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" vote="355" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
					<sub_unit type="Township" name="Springfield" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" vote="43" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" vote="2388" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
					<sub_unit type="Township" name="Westfield" geog_id="null">
						<result candidate_ref="1" vote="8" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
						<result candidate_ref="2" vote="927" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					</sub_unit>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The Centinel of Freedom (Newark, NJ).  February 17, 1807.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">New-Jersey Journal (Elizabethtown, NJ).  February 17, 1807.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">The True American (Trenton, NJ).  February 23, 1807.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Shaw, William H.  History of Essex and Hudson Counties, New Jersey.  Vol. 1.  Philadelphia: Everts and Peck, 1884.  212-213.</reference>
</election_record>                                                                                                                               
