<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" label="New Hampshire 1812 U.S. Senate, Ballot 9" type="Legislative" iteration="Ninth Ballot" date="1812-12" election_id="nh.ussenate.9.1812" handle="10427/26079" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="U.S. Senate" office_id="ON127" scope="Federal">
		<role title="U.S. Senator" scope="State">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="J. K. Smith" name_id="SJ0517" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="1"/>
				<candidate name="John Goddard" name_id="GJ0185" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="2"/>
				<candidate name="scattering" name_id="null" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="3"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2006-07-10">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="89" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="83" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="3" vote_total="4" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09833" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="New Hampshire" geog_id="null">
				<sub_unit type="null" name="House of Representatives" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="89" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="83" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="3" vote="4" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09833" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09840" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<note resp="Philip Lampi">On December 12, 1812 another ballot was held in the House and Jedediah K. Smith (R) was chosen, but that election was not concurred by the Senate, so there was no choice.</note>
					<note resp="Philip Lampi">Eighty nine making a choice, Mr. Smith was elected on the part of the House. In the Senate on motion to concur with the House, Yeas - Messrs. Ham, Folsom, Plumer, Quarles, Fisk, and Darling - Nays - Messrs. Adams, Sanborn, Jackson, Vose, Kimball, and Russell. So the Senate did not concur.</note>
					<note resp="Philip Lampi">"In spite of their nominal majorities in the legislature, the Republicans of New Hampshire in 1812 were fatally weakened by the defection of their Peace party members.  This not only led to their defeat in the presidential and congressional elections but made itself dramatically evident in their failure, during two full sessions, to elect a United States senator.  Responsibility for this debacle lay with Josiah Sanborn of Epsom, who had been elected to the senate as a Republican but who belonged in spirit to the Peace party (fn: Plumer to William Plumer, Jr.  December 5, 1812, Letters 4, Plumer Papers (Library of Congress)).  He voted against all Republicans nominated by his colleagues and insisted upon the election of John Goddard, who, since his electoral vote against Madison, had of course become anathema to the party stalwarts.  The legislature finally ajourned without electing a senator, thus permitting the Federalists to send Jeremiah Mason to the Senate in 1813."  The Ninth State.  278.</note>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.09833">Concord Gazette (Concord, NH).  December 29, 1812.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Turner, Lynn Warren.  The Ninth State: New Hampshire's Formative Years.  Chapel Hill, NC: The University of North Carolina Press, 1983.  278.</reference>
</election_record>
