<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record label="Massachusetts 1806 Senate President, Ballot 4" type="Legislative" iteration="Fourth Ballot" date="1806" election_id="ma.senatepresident.4.1806" handle="10427/28161" xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="Senate President" office_id="ON098" scope="State">
		<role title="Senate President" scope="State">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="John Bacon" name_id="BJ0484" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="1"/>
				<candidate name="Harrison G. Otis" name_id="OH0028" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="2"/>
				<candidate name="scattering" name_id="null" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="3"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2006-08-14">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="19" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="18" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="3" vote_total="2" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10460" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10461" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10462" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"In the afternoon, the balloting was resumed; but with no better success. - In this dilemma, it was moved, that the Senior Senator should be appointed to preside as Chairman, until a President shall be appointed. A debate ensued. - this appointment was opposed by Messrs. Otis, Gore, Phillips, Brigham and Bliss, as unprecedented, unconstitutional, and tending to embarrass the proceedings of the Government. The motion was advocated by Messrs. Hill, Dana, Howe and Smith, on the ground that the Constitution was silent on the subject when the President should be chosen; that the two branches could meet together, fill the vacancies in the Senate and then elect their President. A motion to amend the motion, by making the Senior Senator the permanent President was opposed by the democratic side of the board, and negatived 20 to 19. The original motion, That the Senior Senator should preside as Chairman of the Board, was put by the Hon. Mr. Bacon (who acted as Senior Member;) when the Yeas were found to be 19 - The Nays 19 - He then declared the motion carried in the affirmative. - A question then arose who was the Senior Senator - there being two Senators (Messrs. Bacon and Hastings) who were elected the same year; A committee was raised, consisting of Messrs. Hill, Dana, and Otis to report on the subject; who reported in favor of Mr. Bacon, he took the Chair."  Columbian Centinel. Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  May 31, 1806.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"The Senate resumed the business of the election of a President; but as in the forenoon, was ineffectual. A motion was finally made declaring, The eldest member should preside as President pro tem until a choice could be made. The votes were taken on this motion by yeas and nays and stool thus - Federal 19, Democratic 19. The Chairman (Hon. Mr. Bacon) who was the democratic candidate, after a few remarks declared his vote in favour of himself. On this decison, a variety of debate ensued on the constitutionality of this mode of procedure and on the question whether the Hon. Chairman was the senior member in that body. A committee was at length appointed to ascertain and report was the eldest member."  Connecticut Herald (New Haven, CT).  June 3, 1806.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Massachusetts" geog_id="null">
				<sub_unit type="null" name="State Senate" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="19" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="18" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="3" vote="2" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10460" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10461" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10462" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Columbian Centinel. Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  May 31, 1806.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Hampshire Federalist (Springfield, MA).  June 2, 1806.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10461">Connecticut Herald (New Haven, CT).  June 3, 1806.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10460">The True American and Commercial Advertiser (Philadelphia, PA).  June 3, 1806.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">New-England Palladium (Boston, MA).  June 6, 1806.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Political Observatory (Walpole, NH).  June 6, 1806.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.10462">Middlebury Mercury (Middlebury, VT).  June 11, 1806.</reference>
</election_record>
