<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record label="Massachusetts 1806 House of Representatives, Whately" type="General" iteration="First Ballot" date="1806-05" election_id="ma.staterepresentative.whately.1806" handle="10427/69443" xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="House of Representatives" office_id="ON064" scope="State">
		<role title="State Representative" scope="Town">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="Phineas Frary" name_id="FP0059" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="1"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="Gideon Dickinson" name_id="DG0072" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="2"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2014-12-15">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="44" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="32" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"COMMUNICATION. Mr. Butler, Having seen some remarks in the Republican Spy, on the choice of a Representative for the town of Whately, I request you to publish the following statement which will show that they are false and designed for no other purpose than to wound the feelings of an honest, worthy man. The Spy states, 'that Major Frary gained his election by a majority of three votes, and with a nota bene, that he had three sons at meeting and that more an two thirds of the voters of the town have signed a remonstrance against the proceedings.' When the real facts are known, every body will see, what regard our good democrats have for truth, as well as for the rights of electors, both of which they violate, with equal indifference, to subserve their personal or party interest. On the first Monday of May a meeting of the town was called for the choice of a representative - 80 voters were present and on the affirmative of the question, whether we should send a Representative, was a majority of seven. Major Frary was then elected - he had 44 votes and Gideon Dickinson had 32 - leaving a majority of 12 - The democrats then drew up something which they called a remonstrance in the form following: 'We the subscribers inhabitants of the town of Whately being disappointed by a vote of a small number of the inhabitants out of their usual practice so send a representative to the General Court, we wish the selectmen to issue a warrant and assemble the inhabitant of said town, so see if they cannot come to some method to ease the minds of the inhabitants.' Tho this thing, there were but 64 signers, some of whom were not voters, wheras there are 142 legal voters in the town of Whately. - The Selectmen called a new meeting two of whom were opposed to sending a representative, and a commitee of five was chosen to give Major Frary, as they expressed it, such instruction as they should think proper, and to endeavor to prevent his going. They appointed a place, and sent workd to the Major to make his appearance - but he thought it as little becoming him to make his appearance, as them to call for him - the committee accordingly adjourned. These are the facts as the Clerk of the town will testify. Major Frary was chosen by a majority of 12 instead of 3 -  not one half signed the petition instead of two-thirds - The meeting, was legal, and all the proceedings were legal - Major Frary was elected - but the democrats, being disappointed, drew up their petition, which does as little honor to their heads, as their falsehoods do their hearts."  Hampshire Gazette (Northampton, MA).  May 21, 1806.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Massachusetts" geog_id="null">
				<sub_unit type="Town" name="Whately" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="44" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="32" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Hampshire Gazette (Northampton, MA).  May 21, 1806.</reference>
</election_record>
