<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record label="Massachusetts 1812 Selectman, Springfield" type="General" iteration="First Ballot" date="1812-03" election_id="ma.selectmen.springfield.1812" handle="10427/69921" xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="Selectman" office_id="ON097" scope="Town">
		<role title="Selectman" scope="Town">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="Moses Chapin" name_id="CM0110" affiliation="supported by both parties" affiliation_id="A10" candidate_num="1"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="Judah Chapin" name_id="CJ0997" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="2"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="Joshua Frost" name_id="FJ0132" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="3"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="Eleazer Wright" name_id="WE0207" affiliation="Republican" affiliation_id="A03" candidate_num="4"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="George Blake" name_id="BG0047" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="5"/>
				<candidate name="Thomas Dwight" name_id="DT0078" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="6"/>
				<candidate name="John Hooker" name_id="HJ1146" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="7"/>
				<candidate name="George Bliss" name_id="BG0048" affiliation="Federalist" affiliation_id="A01" candidate_num="8"/>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2014-05-01">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="519" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="283" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="3" vote_total="283" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="4" vote_total="280" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="5" vote_total="274" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="6" vote_total="272" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="7" vote_total="272" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="8" vote_total="271" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">The Hampshire Federalist of April 2, 1812 lists the Federalist as "Town Ticket" and the Republicans as the "U.S. Armoury Ticket".</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Through the scandalous interference of the Agents of the General Government in the municipal elections of the People, democratic Selectmen have been chosen in Springfield.  To revolutionize this federal town was one of the objects of the famous June law. ... It is known that the United States have a large manufactory of firearms in Springfield, in which about 230 persons are employed at high wages; and who are pledged when hired to vote with the democrats:- And it will excite the highest degree of indignation in the breast of every independent citizen, when informed that one hundred and sixty of these pledged persons voted in the choice of town officers, and thus gave the small majority stated; though more than two thirds of then independent electors of then town are decidedly federal."  Columbian Centinel. Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  March 28, 1812.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Springfield Election. The election for town officers in Springfield, gives a striking proof of the blessed practical effects of the new Law. Two thirds of the day was spent by nearly six hundred persons in choosing a moderator, which has commonly been done in two thirds of a minute, and the same man elected. .... The town of Springfield is as decidedly Federal as almost any town of its size, exclusive of the United State Armoury. A small proportion of the inhabitants, who do not derive a great part of their income from the Treasury of the United States, is democratic. Consider what influence 120,000 dollars, annually expended in such a place will have, when directed to one point. That it has been the constant endeavor of those who have to direct the expenditure of this money, thereby to further democracy, can never be denied. There are in the Armoury, with a few exceptions, no men who are not pledged to democracy. .... A majority of the armourers have no more connection with the town, no more interest in it or it's proceedings that if they lived an hundred miles off. .... Add to all this the influence created by employing at high wages and ready pay, in relation to the Armoury, though not in it, men who are now democrats or men who it is hoped may become such. If influence, however, was all the Federalists had to contend with, as great and enormous as it is, they would have withstood it. But much more than this was done. An association was drawn up and presented to the armourers to sign, in which they were required to pledge themselves to vote for the democratic candidates. And whether the alternative of immediate dismission was stated to them or not, it was as well understood as if the order had come signed by President Madison himself."  Hampshire Federalist (Springfield, MA).  April 2, 1812.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"Moses Chapin and Edward Pynchon, Esq's. (Federalist) were also on some of the Armoury tickets. .... 280 were necessary to a choice. The above statement show that four Selectmen, one Federalist and three Democrats were chosen. Edward Pynchon, Esq. the federal candidate for Town Clerk was chosen without opposition."  Hampshire Federalist (Springfield, MA).  April 2, 1812.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Massachusetts" geog_id="null">
				<sub_unit type="Town" name="Springfield" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="519" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="283" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="3" vote="283" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="4" vote="280" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="5" vote="274" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="6" vote="272" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="7" vote="272" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="8" vote="271" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Columbian Centinel. Massachusetts Federalist (Boston, MA).  March 28, 1812.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi">Hampshire Federalist (Springfield, MA).  April 2, 1812.</reference>
</election_record>
