<?xml version="1.0"?>
<election_record xmlns="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" label="Pennsylvania 1795 Sheriff, Delaware County" type="General" iteration="First Ballot" date="1795" election_id="pa.sheriff.delawarecounty.1795" handle="10427/60811" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dca.tufts.edu/aas http://dca.tufts.edu/schema/aas/electionRecord.xsd">
	<office name="Sheriff" office_id="ON100" scope="County">
		<role title="Sheriff" scope="County">
			<ballot>
				<candidate name="William Maddock" name_id="MW0297" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="1"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
				<candidate name="Abraham Dicks" name_id="DA0077" affiliation="null" affiliation_id="null" candidate_num="2"><note resp="Philip Lampi">Elected.</note></candidate>
			</ballot>
			<overview status="Version 0.5" modified="2011-09-15">
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="1" vote_total="480" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<candidate_summary candidate_ref="2" vote_total="423" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.05471" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.05472" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">"'For some time previous to the election, four persons offered themselves Candidates for the said office, amongst whom was William Maddock. For three of the Candidates, 1112 Electors were divided agreeably to the following numbers, viz. 423, 400 and 289 -- independent of these Maddock had 480 votes.  This man, who in the beginning of the revolution was an Officer in the militia of Chester County, thought proper to forsake the standard and cause of his country, and to retreat within the British lines, and continued there till after the peace of 1783 - in the meantime he was attainted of high-treason, and stood, till the later pardon of the Governor of Pennsylvania, on record as a traitor.  If the dignity of government, the peace of Delaware County, and the confident character of Governor Mifflin, are consulted upon the occasion, there is great cause to believe that Mr. Maddock will not be honoured, considering his former conduct, with the commission of High Sheriff.' A Citizen of Delaware County."  The Aurora. General Advertiser (Philadelphia, PA).  November 9, 1795.</note>
				<note resp="Philip Lampi">The Original Returns contain a number of letters protesting the election of William Maddock as improper or illegal.  There is also, among the Original Returns a statement asserting that the "Pardon by the Governor of Pennsylvania, and the Act of Congress, entitled "An act to establish an uniform rule of naturalization" restores to William Maddock "all the rights of a Citizen of Pennsylvania."  There are also several letters in support signed by over 160 citizens of Delaware County.</note>
			</overview>
			<admin_unit type="State" name="Pennsylvania" geog_id="null">
				<sub_unit type="County" name="Delaware" geog_id="null">
					<result candidate_ref="1" vote="480" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<result candidate_ref="2" vote="423" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
					<reference type="page_image" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.05471" resp="Philip Lampi"/>
				</sub_unit>
			</admin_unit>
		</role>
	</office>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.05471">Original Election Returns.  Pennsylvania State Archives, Harrisburg.</reference>
	<reference type="citation" resp="Philip Lampi" urn="tufts:central:dca:MS115:MS115.001.DO.05472">The Aurora. General Advertiser (Philadelphia, PA).  November 9, 1795.</reference>
</election_record>
